Take five colours: red, black, blue, green and purple.
以五种颜色为例：红色、黑色、蓝色、绿色和紫色。
How do they make you feel?
它们会让你有怎样的感受呢？
It‘s a question of supreme significance to designers and marketers.
这是一个对设计师和营销人员来说具有极其重要意义的问题。
British fashion designer Wayne Hemingway explored this topic in a BBC radio programme about the psychology of colour.
英国时装设计师韦恩·海明威在BBC一档关于色彩心理学的广播节目中探讨了这个话题。
You can read a summary of his ideas below.
你可以在下面读到他的简要观点。
Do you agree with him?
你同意他的看法吗？
Or do you think the meaning of colour depends on the culture you live in?
或者你认为颜色的意义取决于你所生活的文化背景吗？
Red is, of course, considered auspicious in China.
当然，红色在中国被认为是吉祥的。
But he points out that it’s a powerful colour wherever you go, with some serious scientific credentials.
但他指出，无论在什么地方，红色都是一种很有力量的颜色，并且有一些可靠的科学依据。
Studies have indicated that red “raises blood pressure”, and claim that it stands out from other colours thanks to its long wavelength.
研究表明，红色“会使血压升高”，并且声称由于其波长较长，红色在其他颜色中很突出。
Hemingway says it appears to be “coming towards you”, and so is useful for emergency and alarm signs, and also for conveying “urgency” in general.
海明威说，红色看起来像是“向你扑面而来”，所以它适用于紧急情况和警报标志，并且总体上也用于传达“紧迫性”。
That‘s why he thinks red sale posters seem to yell at us: “Quick, buy it now!”
这就是为什么他认为红色的促销海报似乎在对我们大喊：“快，现在就买！”
Black has a different sense.
黑色有不同的含义。
In the West it’s associated with death but that hasn‘t stopped it from being a prestigious and mysterious colour.
在西方，它与死亡有关，但这并没有阻止它成为一种高贵而神秘的颜色。
Hemingway says it’s the colour of luxury brands: things like “glossy black limousines” and “designer watches” are often black.
海明威说，它是奢侈品牌的颜色：像“富有光泽的黑色豪华轿车”和“名牌手表”之类的东西通常是黑色的。
“When used as the main colour in branding, black is very powerful and sophisticated.”
“在品牌推广中用作主色调时，黑色非常强大且时尚精致。”
Blue, by contrast, is cool and tranquil.
相比之下，蓝色是冷静且宁静的。
The colour is a constant presence in our lives, says Hemingway, being the colour of the sky and the sea.
海明威说，蓝色是天空和大海的颜色，在我们的生活中一直存在。
That gives it an air of reliability, which makes it a firm choice with “banks and corporations”.
这赋予了它一种可靠的气质，这使得它成为“银行和公司”的坚定选择。
Hemingway says this is also why emergency services often choose the colour.
海明威说，这也是应急服务部门经常选择这种颜色的原因。
A blue uniform can, for example, indicate “the cool competence of a nurse”.
例如，蓝色的制服可以体现“护士冷静干练的能力”。
Green is, unsurprisingly, the colour of nature and the environment.
不出所料，绿色是大自然和地球环境的颜色。
Marketers understand that giving a product green packaging creates the impression it is environmentally friendly.
营销人员明白，给产品使用绿色包装会让人觉得它是环保的。
But savvy customers are also aware of this - and now think twice before blindly swallowing environmental claims.
但精明的消费者也意识到了这一点——现在他们在盲目相信有关环保宣传之前会三思。
Hemingway also says that green is the colour of growth and movement: it‘s used to indicate ’go‘ on traffic lights.
海明威还说，绿色是成长和运动的颜色：它在交通信号灯中用于表示“通行”。
Finally, we have purple, which is associated with valuable things.
最后，我们来说说紫色，它与珍贵的东西联系在一起。
In the past, purple dye was expensive because it was very difficult to produce, and it became the colour worn by royalty in many Western countries.
过去，紫色染料很昂贵，因为生产起来非常困难，它成为了许多西方国家皇室着装的颜色。
These days, companies still use purple to make their product seem more exclusive, whether they’re selling chocolate or cigarettes.
如今，公司仍然使用紫色使他们的产品看起来更独特，无论是销售巧克力还是香烟。